"Power"
（カブト）今は　限界かな。
I guess that's the limit.
（サクラ）さっきの穴の？
That hole from earlier...?
（シセル）あの人　村の防人だわ。
That man...
is a village guard!
また会おう。
Let's meet again.
（ヤマト）逃げたか。
He escaped...
（ディソナス）ヤマトさん　彼らはいったい？
Mr. Yamato... Who is he?
（ヤマト）説明します。
I'll explain.
（ヤマト）これは増援が必要だな。
We're going to need reinforcements.
（レオ）来た　来た～！
I got a bite!
（レオ）やった～！
Got it!
ほい　まけとくよ！
Here... This one's on me!
（ソラ）ありがとう　おじさん！
Thank you, mister.
アンタら　トニカ村の人なんだろ？
（ドック）えっ？
You're from Tonika Village,
aren't you?
ほら　防人の。
Huh?
You know, the guard.
ああ…　ええ
クビになりましたけど。
Oh...
Well, yes... But I was fired.
ひどいケガしてるみたいだけど
何かあったんかい？
You seem to be badly wounded.
What happened?
いえ　ちょっと事故しちゃって。
Oh, just an accident.
安いよ！
とれたてだよ！
We've got cheap prices!
This just came in!
ほら　見てってくれ！
Stop by!
（レオ）先生！
おっと！
Sensei!
ごめんなさい！
Whoa!
I'm sorry!
やったぜ　大漁！
I did it!
Look how many!
おおっ！
俺の腕のおかげ！
Wow!
Gotta hand it to my skill!
（ランド）エサを選んだのは
僕だけどね。
But I chose the bait.
エサかえるまで　ボウズだったろ？
You didn't catch a single fish
until you changed bait!
（ファズ）魚か　僕　苦手なんだよな。
Fish, eh?
I don't care for fish.
ファズ　贅沢言うなよ。
Faz, don't be so picky.
食べにくいし。
They're a pain to eat.
生臭いのダメだし。
I don't like things that smell fishy.
ママだったら　もっと別の…。
Mom would make
something different...
オメエのママは　もういねえんだよ！
Your mom is gone!
それ　教室でも
口ずさんでたよね？
You used to hum
that tune in class too.
何か聞こえるんだってさ。
She says she can
hear something.
聞こえる？
Hear?
今も？
Even now?
always chasing after your shadow
itsu made mo oikakete iru anata no zanzo wo
when you dream, your face looks like it did before
yume ni miru yokogao ha ano koro no mama de
you run into the tall grass and disappear
se no takai kusanami ni hashiri satte kieta
I push through the memories and follow you
omoidasu kioku wo kakewake atoo uboku ha
it's frustrating as I run out of breath and in the end I'm unable to reach you
modokashiku mo iki wo kirashite saigo ha todokazu ni
far away
tooku
how many years ago was it?
nannenmae no koto desho
I left my heart at that place
nidoto modorenai ano basho ni
where I can never return
oite kite shimatta boku no kokoro sa
if this is a dream, if I can't get it back
moshimo yume naraba tori modosenai no nara
then how can I tell you how I feel?
kono kimochi ha do shite utaereba ii no
I'm still chasing after the shadow from that day
imadani oikakete iru ano hi no zanzo wo
though I spend my days in sorrow
kanashimi ni ake kurenagara mo ima
I'll live on in this world without you
anata naki sekai de boku wa ikiru yo
Do you know the survivor
from the village, Shiseru?
（サクラ）村の生き残りの方って→
シセルさんと
お知り合いなんですか？
Yes, he and I were
childhood friends.
（シセル）うん　彼とは幼なじみなの。
We lived together as kids.
子供の頃は一緒に暮らしてたし
お兄ちゃんって呼んでた。
I used to called him, "Brother."
I still do.
今もだけどね。
I hadn't seen him at all lately.
（シセル）最近は全然
会ってなかったけど→
He put on a lot of weight.
また随分　太ってたな。
But I'm relieved that
he's still his old self.
でも　ちっとも変わってなくて
安心した。
He protected five kids!
５人も子供守ったし。
（サクラ）すごいです。
That's amazing.
What's the matter with you?
さっきから何よ？
I feel so bloated.
（ナルト）何か　腹がタプタプする。
Can you wait here?
ここで待ってて。
I'll see if he's around.
いるか確認してみる。
Run away!
逃げるんだ！
Huh?
What is it?
あ？
何？
Brother?
お兄ちゃん？
Sensei!
先生？
なんで逃げるのさ？
Why're we running away?
The symbol on the headbands
of those shinobi...
あ　あの忍の額当てのマーク。
The ones who attacked
the village wore the same mark!
村を襲った連中だ。
（みんな）えっ！？
Hold it.
Please wait.
We mean no harm...
待てよ。
ちょっと待ってください。
私たち
別に怪しい者じゃなくて…。
"DANGER! DO NOT CROSS"
Leo, don't!
It's dangerous!
レオ！　ダメだよ　危ないよ。
But we have to get away!
でも逃げなきゃ。
C'mon, Sensei!
さあ　先生！
Mina...
ミィナ　行くよ。
Let's go!
Sensei!
— Sensei!
— What'll we do?!
（レオ）先生！
（ファズたち）先生！
Naruto!
Right!
ナルト！
おう！
I'm sorry...
ごめんね。
What's happening?
え…。
どういうこと？
Brother?!
お兄ちゃん？
You're heavy!
重ぇな！
I'm sorry, I overreacted.
（ドック）早とちりして　すみません。
The children did it for my sake...
子供たちも　僕のために…。
I'm sorry.
（レオたち）ごめんなさい。
Yeah...
おう！
You know Shiseru.
シセルはご存じですね。
I'm Dokku. I was their teacher
in the village.
僕はドック。
村では
子供たちの先生をしていました。
This is Leo.
彼はレオ。
こんにちは！
Hi!
You're gutsy.
お前　勇気あんな！
You could say that!
まあな。
Lando and Faz.
（ドック）ランドにファズ。
Hi.
Hello...
どうも。
こんにちは。
She's Sora.
（ドック）彼女はソラ。
こんにちは。
Hello.
Nice to meet you.
こんにちは。
And... Leo's younger sister, Mina.
それと　レオの妹のミィナ。
Huh? Isn't that vest kind of big?
ん？　そのベスト　大きくね？
Oh, that's mine.
ああ　それ。　僕のだったけど→
But she likes it and refuses
to part with it, so...
彼女が気に入って離さないから
そのまま。
Oh... Well, nice to meet you.
へぇ　よろしくな。
Huh?
Oh, sorry...
ああ　ごめんね。
What's wrong, Mina?
どうしたの？　ミィナ。
Hidden treasure?
（ヤマト）秘宝か。
But why would Kabuto want
something like that?
（ヤマト）カブトがなぜ
そんなものを欲するのか→
It's not like him.
しっくりこないな。
Just what was there anyway?
（サイ）そもそも　あそこに
何があったんでしょうね？
I used to be a scholar and conducted
archeological research.
（ディソナス）私は　以前は学者で→
考古学の研究をしていました。
In particular, I studied quite
a bit about "the Hole."
特にホールについては
ずいぶんと調査もしました。
These are the results
of my research
これは　ホールの伝承とされている
古文書の研究成果です。
on the ancient writings about
the legend of "the Hole."
I believe that actual historical events
are described in them.
これには　ある歴史的事象が
描かれているように思われます。
The master of the Great Lake
once created the "Ama no Goko,"
太古の主が創造なされた
天の矛は→
but its power was taken away
by evil.
けがれたものによって
力を奪われた。
This evil hated everything...
けがれたものは
すべてを憎んでいたので→
and by using the "power,"
it tried to destroy the world.
力を使い　世界を壊そうとした。
The "power" covered
the world and...
世界を覆いし　その力は→
was on the verge of destroying it.
もはや
世界を滅ぼすところだった。
But just by chance,
亡きものの一つが
偶然　力の欠片を拾った。
one of the dead picked up
a shard of the "power."
And it turned crimson...
and was enveloped in flames.
亡きものは
赤き炎をまとったものとなり→
And it took revenge on
the tainted one.
けがれたものに復讐をした。
After seven hours
of fighting in purgatory...
七つ時の煉獄での戦いの末→
finally, the one in flames
emerged victorious.
ついには　炎をまとったものは
勝利した。
In order to prevent the "power"
from being stolen
赤きものは　力を
次のけがれたものから守るため→
by the next evil,
the crimson one divided "power"
into seven sounds,
七つの音にわけて
そのさえずりを封じた。
and sealed away this "Saezuri."
That's a quick summary.
以上が簡単な要約ですが。
"Saezuri"...
さえずり…
それが　カブトが盗んだものですか。
That's what Kabuto stole?
うむ　実在すればですが。
That's if it really exists.
Ama no Hoko...
What could it be?
（サイ）天の矛　何でしょうね？
This is just a guess.
But it's something that
surpasses human knowledge.
（ディソナス）私には　何か人智を
超えたものの存在に思えます。
Undoubtedly...
（ヤマト）確かに　あのホールには→
One gets the feeling that a deep,
dark secret lies hidden in that "Hole."
何か大きな秘密が
隠されているように感じますね。
However, even if they conspired
to steal the treasure,
（ディソナス）しかし
秘宝狙いの悪行とはいえ→
that's no reason to kill
innocent villagers.
罪のない村の人々までが
殺されるいわれなどないはず。
Such an act is unforgivable!
こんなことが
許されるはずなどない！
I totally agree.
（ヤマト）同感です。
Kabuto will be made to
answer to his crimes.
カブトには　必ず罪を償わせます。
I'm counting on you.
よろしくお願いします。
Naruto.
ナルト。
Everyone's going to
the outdoor bath.
Huh? I get to bathe with you, Sakura?
みんなで　露天風呂　行こうって。
えっ！？
サクラちゃんと混浴？
As if
（サクラ）んなわけないでしょ！
- Wow...
No wonder
he's a legendary hero...
（レオ）すっげえ！
（ランド）さすが　伝説の英雄。
Hey, if you guys train,
maybe you'll be able to do it too.
さあ　オメエらも修業すれば
できるかもしんねえぞ。
Really?!
本当！？
フン！
Damn! Once more!
ぷはっ！
クソッ　もう一度。
You're famous even in
a rural place like this.
I thought you'd be more
fierce and scary.
ナルト君は　こんな田舎でも
有名人だから→
I'm shocked at how young
and easy-going you are!
もっと強面で　怖い人だって
思ってたけど→
若くて気さくなんで驚いた。
ハハッ。
It's amazing...
Your body must store
immense power.
すごいな！
その体ん中に　とてつもない力を
秘めてるんだね。
いや～。
When I was your age,
I couldn't even save a single girl.
ん？
僕なんか
キミくらいの歳のときでも→
女の子１人　助けらんなかった。
Shiseru... What are those...?
These scars?
シセルさん　それ…。
I fell from a cliff
a long, long time ago.
ああ　この傷？
大昔に崖から落っこちたの。
What?!
About 50 meters, maybe?
えっ！？
５０メートルくらい？
Luckily, I fell onto a tree!
運よく木に落ちて　助かったけど
フフッ。
But how...?
なんでまた。
I was careless.
私が不注意だったのよね。
Stop it, Shiseru.
- Brother kept warning me too.
- It's dangerous.
((よせって　シセル。
やあっ　それ！))
Wanna fight?!
（シセル）お兄ちゃんが
あんなに注意してくれてたのに。
わあ！
Did Dokku...?
Uh-huh.
He grabbed me immediately...
ドックさんが？
うん　とっさに掴んでくれたの。
and held on tight
for what seemed like an hour.
もしかしたら　１時間くらい
ずっと。
I hated exercise and
my arms were weak.
運動嫌いで腕力もなかったから
情けなくて　悔しくて。
I was so frustrated
and angry at myself...
If I had let Shiseru die...
((キャー！))
もし　あのまま
シセルが死んじゃってたら→
I...
Really, it was all my fault.
僕…。
本当　全部自分が悪いんだから。
It wasn't his fault at all.
お兄ちゃんのせいなんかじゃ
ないのに。
I hated myself for being weak,
so I was determined to be a guard.
（ドック）弱い自分がイヤだったから→
And I did my best, but...
頑張って防人になったし
努力もしたけど。
I wasn't suited to it, after all.
やっぱり
向いてなかったみたいで。
Then we drifted apart.
Even when I went to see him,
there was a wall between us...
（シセル）それから離れ離れになって。
たまに会いに行っても
なんか気まずかったし。
And before I knew it,
we were like strangers.
いつの間にか
疎遠になっちゃってたな。
But that night...
でも　あの夜は
僕に　もっと…。
If only I...
I was so happy to see him
after so long, but...
久々に会えて
すごく嬉しかったけど。
If only I had more power...
もっと力があれば　もっと…。
More strength...
Brother's probably
beating himself up right now.
お兄ちゃん
きっと悔しかっただろうな。
I wish I could've saved
more people!
もっと助けたかったよ！
He lost so many people
who were dear to him.
大切な人たちを　みんな失って…。
I can't do it!
It's impossible!
クソ！
ダメ～。
ムリだよ　アハハ。
Naruto! Show us the trick
to doing it!
ナルト兄ちゃん
コツ教えて。
Sure!
おう！
I noticed something was
wrong in the village
（ドック）
村の異変に気づいたのは→
just around bedtime.
そろそろ
寝ようとしてた頃でした。
All of a sudden, the village
was engulfed in a sea of flames.
村は　あっという間に
火の海になって→
A shinobi attacked me too.
僕も忍に襲われたんです。
((うわっ！))
He was so strong,
I thought I was going to die.
強くて
もうダメだと思ったんですが…。
Suddenly, he stopped moving.
It was as though some
puppet strings had been cut.
急に　動きが止まったりして→
まるで
操り糸が切れたみたいな…。
The Reanimation Jutsu is
a Forbidden Jutsu
穢土転生という術は→
that uses the sacrificed body
as a vessel...
生け贄を器に
死者の魂を縛りつけて→
It imbeds the soul of a dead person
and forces it back to life.
It was believed that
強制的によみがえらせる
禁術です。
only the Second Hokage and
Orochimaru knew how to use it.
術を扱えたのは　二代目火影と→
It seems that under
the Akatsuki's control, he's failed...
大蛇丸だけだと
思われていましたが→
もっとも　ヤツも
暁連中の制御に失敗したり→
and the jutsu still hasn't
been perfected.
まだまだ術は不完全なようだ…。
Do you know about the "Saezuri"?
ドックさんは　さえずりを
ご存じですか？
The ancient writing?
古文書のですか？
That's what Kabuto seeks.
カブトは　それを狙っていたようです。
Do you know any thing about
the "Saezuri" that could help us?
さえずりについて
何か知っていたり→
参考になるようなことは
ありませんか？
Take this and run!
Throw it away somewhere,
that's fine.
((これを持って逃げろ！
However, never say
a word of this to anyone!
どこかに捨てても構わん。
ただし　このことは→
(絶対に他言無用だ))
No... not especially.
I see...
いえ…　特には。
We'll be joining up with
the Security Unit tomorrow
そうですか。
and begin our pursuit.
我々は　明日にでも
町の警備隊と協力して→
However, there is the guard
that was captured.
ヤツの捜索を行うつもりです。
Just to be safe, I'll assign
someone to keep watch over you.
ですが　あの捕まった
防人のこともありますし→
用心のために
あなたの周辺も見張らせます。
Thank you.
Also, about the children
you rescued.
ありがとうございます。
それと　助けられた
お子さんたちのことなんですが。
The town's willing to
make arrangements
with an institution to take them in.
町の施設が受け入れを
準備してくださるそうです。
What would you like to do?
どうされますか？
They're fast asleep.
Yes...
ぐっすり寝てる。
うん。
The kids actually laughed today.
今日　あの子たち
笑ってたね。
It's the first time since that night...
あの夜から　初めて…。
Kabuto...
You're so violent with your jutsu.
（カカシ）カブト…。
You didn't have to
kill them all.
（カブト）アンタの組んだ術式は
荒々しい。
別に　皆殺しにする必要
なかったのに。
"BUT IT'S FUN"
For you, right?
"OROCHIMARU WOULD HAVE DONE THE SAME THING"
アンタがだろ。
I've improved the jutsu technique
by adjusting it to my chakra.
フンッ！
術式は　僕のチャクラに合わせて
改良した。
It'll be easy to control this time.
It's time I also tested...
今度は　うまく制御できる。
situations involving intent
and memory.
そろそろ　意思と記憶のある状態も
試しておかないとね。
"BY THE WAY, I STILL DON'T HAVE ENOUGH"
"THERE MIGHT BE SOMEONE WHO HAS IT"
So? Do I have to lock for it?
で？　また僕が探すの？
"THAT'S BEEN THE ORDER SINCE THE START"
You really like to make me work.
ホント　人使いが荒いな　アンタは。
Well, that's fine.
This just gives me something
to look forward to.
まあ　でもいいや。
楽しみが増えたし。
"WHAT?"
Naruto...
ナルト君…。
I wonder why I can't fly
nande kanaa sora ga tobenai no wa
even though in my dreams, I have wings
yume no naka no boku wa hane ga haeten no ni
I'm going to surpass my limits and leave this place
genkai wo koete tobidasou koko kara
I'll drive away my loneliness with you
samishisa fuki tobasu kimi to kimi to
"I love you" and "good bye" have disappeared
i love you mo sayonara mo ienakatta
leaving me here incomplete
koko ni fukanzen na boku dake wo nokoshite
you still haven't taught me the song of love
ai no uta kimi ni mada tsutaetenai yo
of this dazzling world
dokomademo mabushiku kagayaku sekai wo
of this song
kono uta wo
I want to see you!
Papa, Mama!
I'm so lonely!
Why are you lonely?!
They're with you always!
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Power - Episode 3"
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
Get out! Get out!
美空ひばりです。
Get out! Get out! Get out! Get out!
Get out! Get out!!
では最後まで　ごゆっくり→
お楽しみください。
（宮本）『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！　にっぽんの歌』。
（松丸）今回はご覧の豪華歌手
１２人の皆さんによる→